Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Kathryn and today we're talking about things at the office.
我是Kathryn，今天我们聊聊办公室里的那些事。
That's right.
没错。
We are at the office but this time we are going to ask our boss or manager for a raise.
我们在办公室，但这次我们要向老板或经理要求加薪。
Alright, so what is this word raise?
好的，那这个“raise”是什么意思呢？
Let's take a look at it in today's vocabulary preview.
让我们在今天的词汇预览中看看。
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
Alright, so we're going to ask for a raise.
好的，所以我们要要求加薪。
So if you are at your office and you talk to your boss and you say, I want a raise,
如果你在办公室跟老板说，我想要加薪，
what does that mean?
那是什么意思？
That means I want more money.
意思是我想要更多钱。
Okay, so I want a raise or increase in my salary.
好的，所以我想要加薪或涨工资。
That's right.
没错。
So a raise is a thing that you ask for and in this case a raise means that you already
所以加薪是你要求的东西，在这种情况下，加薪意味着你已经
work at the company, you already have a salary and you want some more money each month.
在公司工作，已经有薪水，并且想要每个月多拿一些钱。
Okay, so that's what we're going to be talking about today.
好的，这就是我们今天要讨论的内容。
Let's listen to this dialogue.
让我们听听这段对话。
Excuse me sir, may I talk to you?
打扰一下，先生，我能和您谈谈吗？
Bill, sure, come on in.
比尔，当然，进来吧。
What can I do for you?
我能为你做什么？
Well sir, as you know, I have been an employee of this prestigious firm for over 10 years.
嗯，先生，如您所知，我在这家知名公司工作已经超过10年了。
Yes.
是的。
I won't beat around the bush.
我就不拐弯抹角了。
Sir, I would like a raise.
先生，我想要加薪。
I currently have three companies after me and so I decided to talk to you first.
目前有三家公司挖我，所以我决定先和您谈谈。
A raise?
加薪？
Son, I would love to give you a raise but this is just not the right time.
孩子，我很想给你加薪，但现在不是时候。
I understand your position and I know that the current economic downturn has had a negative
我理解您的处境，也知道当前的经济衰退对销售产生了负面
impact on sales but you must also take into consideration my hard work, proactiveness
影响，但您也必须考虑到我十多年来对公司的辛勤工作、积极主动
and loyalty to this company for over a decade.
和忠诚。
Taking into account these factors and considering I don't want to start a brain drain, I'm
考虑到这些因素，并且我不想引发人才流失，我
willing to offer you a 10% raise and an extra five days of vacation time.
愿意给你加薪10%，外加五天额外假期。
How does that sound?
听起来怎么样？
Great.
太好了。
Bill, thank you sir.
比尔，谢谢您，先生。
Before you go, just out of curiosity, what companies were after you?
在你走之前，只是好奇，哪些公司在挖你？
Oh, the electric company, the gas company and the water company.
哦，电力公司、煤气公司和自来水公司。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now, why don't we take a look at Language Takeaway.
现在，我们来看看语言要点。
Language Takeaway
语言要点
So, the conversation we just heard is a conversation between a manager or a boss and the employee.
我们刚才听到的对话是经理或老板与员工之间的对话。
And the employee says, listen, I need to talk to you about something.
员工说，听着，我需要和你谈谈一些事。
I have been an employee at this prestigious firm for over 10 years.
我在这家知名公司工作已经超过10年了。
So prestigious is our first word.
所以“prestigious”是我们的第一个词。
Okay.
好的。
Prestigious is an adjective, right?
“Prestigious”是一个形容词，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
And it means very respected, very well known.
它的意思是备受尊敬、非常知名的。
Esteemed, that's right.
受尊敬的，没错。
So something that is prestigious has a good reputation.
所以某样东西是“prestigious”意味着它有良好的声誉。
Like for example, some universities.
比如，一些大学。
You hear all the time about American universities like Harvard or Yale, which are considered
你经常听到像哈佛或耶鲁这样的美国大学，它们被认为是
to be prestigious universities.
知名大学。
Or the Nobel Peace Prize is a very prestigious award.
或者诺贝尔和平奖是一个非常著名的奖项。
Okay.
好的。
So it's an adjective to describe something that's respectable, well known or esteemed,
所以它是一个形容词，用来描述值得尊敬、知名或受尊敬的，
as you said.
就像你说的。
Exactly.
完全正确。
Alright.
好的。
And what's our next word?
那我们的下一个词是什么？
Our next one is not so happy.
下一个词不太乐观。
This is what we've been experiencing in the global economy this last year or two.
这是过去一两年全球经济一直在经历的。
It's called an economic downturn.
它叫做经济衰退。
Alright.
好的。
So an economic downturn is something negative, as you said.
所以经济衰退是负面的，就像你说的。
So it means that the economy is not doing very well.
它意味着经济状况不太好。
Right.
对。
So economy, economic, you know what this means.
所以经济、经济的，你知道这是什么意思。
But in this case, downturn is the key part of this phrase to slow down or to decrease.
但在这里，“downturn”是这个短语的关键部分，意思是放缓或下降。
So a downturn is a time when less people are making money and less money overall is being
所以衰退是一段时期，更少的人赚钱，总体赚的钱也
earned.
更少。
Okay.
好的。
So an economic downturn.
所以是经济衰退。
Very good.
非常好。
So let me move on to our next word, which is negative impact.
那么让我继续下一个词，它是“负面冲击”。
So the thing working here is the economic downturn and it has had a negative impact
这里起作用的是经济衰退，它对我们的销售，对这家公司的销售产生了负面
on our sales, on this company's sales.
影响。
So a negative impact, as you know from the first word, is not a good thing.
所以“负面冲击”，从第一个词你就能知道，不是好事。
Right.
对。
It's an effect, right?
这是一种影响，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
An effect, but that's negative.
一种影响，但那是负面的。
So it's not a good effect.
所以不是好影响。
So I could say that, Marco, being late has had a negative impact on your work lately.
所以我可以这么说，Marco，最近迟到对你的工作产生了负面影响。
Okay.
好的。
Or the opposite now.
或者反过来。
What if something is a good effect on something?
如果某件事对某物有好的影响呢？
So Marco, your hard work has had a really positive impact on this company lately.
所以Marco，你最近的努力工作对公司产生了非常积极的影响。
All right.
好的。
Good.
很好。
So you can use it negative impact or a positive impact.
所以你可以用“负面影响”或“积极影响”。
All right.
好的。
Right.
对。
So impact again is just the effect that something has on something else.
所以“影响”再次指某事物对另一事物产生的作用。
And while the boss said that he agrees to give him a raise because in part he didn't
而老板说他同意给他加薪，部分原因是
want to start a brain drain.
他不想引发人才流失。
What's that?
那是什么？
Oh, this is a very common phrase you hear about countries.
哦，这是一个关于国家常听到的常见短语。
They have a brain drain or they want to avoid a brain drain.
他们有“人才流失”或想避免“人才流失”。
A drain is the part of a sink or a bathtub where the water goes down.
“流失”是水槽或浴缸里水往下流的部分。
Okay.
好的。
It goes away.
水流走了。
And so brain drain means all the brains or intelligent people or educated people leave
所以“人才流失”意味着所有人才或聪明人、受过教育的人
a country and go to another country.
离开一个国家去另一个国家。
Or in this case, leave a company and go to another company.
或者在这种情况下，离开一家公司去另一家公司。
All right.
好的。
So for example, if all the employees at Apple, maybe they start to quit or they start to
所以举个例子，如果苹果公司的所有员工开始辞职或
move jobs and start to work for maybe Microsoft or Google, that's a brain drain, right?
跳槽去微软或谷歌工作，那就是人才流失，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
Because you're talking about a large number of people.
因为你说的是大量的人。
Maybe they're all unhappy because they say that working at Apple is not very nice.
也许他们都不开心，因为觉得在苹果工作不太好。
So they all leave and go to this other company.
所以他们都离开去了另一家公司。
The same is true with countries.
国家也是一样。
You can have very, very well-educated people who when they stop studying, they want jobs,
你可能有非常非常受过良好教育的人，他们毕业后想找工作，
they all look somewhere else.
都去别处寻找。
They go to America or Mexico or England.
他们去美国、墨西哥或英国。
And so that's called a brain drain because they all go away.
所以那被称为人才流失，因为他们都走了。
Okay.
好的。
So five great phrases right there and words for you.
所以这里有五个很棒的表达和词汇给你。
Let's listen to this dialogue again and we'll be back to take a look at Fluency Builder.
让我们再听一遍这段对话，然后回来看看流利度构建部分。
Excuse me, sir.
打扰一下，先生。
May I talk to you?
我能和您谈谈吗？
Bill.
比尔。
Come on in.
进来吧。
What can I do for you?
我能为你做什么？
Well, sir, as you know, I have been an employee of this prestigious firm for over 10 years.
嗯，先生，如您所知，我在这家知名公司工作已经超过10年了。
Yes.
是的。
I won't beat around the bush.
我就不拐弯抹角了。
Sir, I would like a raise.
先生，我想要加薪。
I currently have three companies after me and so I decided to talk to you first.
目前有三家公司想挖我，所以我决定先和您谈谈。
A raise?
加薪？
Son, I would love to give you a raise, but this is just not the right time.
孩子，我很想给你加薪，但现在不是时候。
I understand your position and I know that the current economic downturn has had a negative
我理解您的处境，也知道当前经济低迷对销售
impact on sales.
产生了负面影响。
But you must also take into consideration my hard work, proactiveness and loyalty to
但您也必须考虑我十多年来对公司的辛勤工作、积极主动和忠诚。
this company for over a decade.
Taking into account these factors and considering I don't want to start a brain drain, I'm willing
考虑到这些因素，以及我不想引发人才流失，我愿意
to offer you a 10% raise and an extra five days of vacation time.
给你加薪10%，外加五天额外假期。
How does that sound?
听起来怎么样？
Great.
太好了。
It's a deal.
成交。
Thank you, sir.
谢谢您，先生。
Before you go, just out of curiosity, what companies were after you?
在你走之前，只是好奇，哪些公司在挖你？
Oh, uh, the electric company, the gas company and the water company.
哦，呃，电力公司、煤气公司和自来水公司。
Okay.
好的。
This first phrase in today's Fluency Builder is one of my favorites.
今天流利度构建中的第一个短语是我最喜欢的之一。
It's something that we say often when we're having a conversation and we want the other
这是我们在对话中经常说的，当我们想让对方
person to just tell us what they're talking about.
直接告诉我们他们在说什么时。
All right.
好的。
So the guy said, you know what?
所以那个人说，你知道吗？
I'm not going to beat around the bush.
我不打算拐弯抹角。
Or you could also say, please don't beat around the bush.
或者你也可以说，请不要拐弯抹角。
So I'm not sure where this phrase comes from, but it means please be direct or I'm going
所以我不确定这个短语的来源，但它意思是请直接点，或者我要
to be direct.
直接说。
I will not wait any longer to tell you what I'm talking about.
我不会再等下去才告诉你我在说什么。
So if somebody is beating around the bush, that means they are not being direct.
所以如果有人拐弯抹角，那意味着他们不直接。
They're not telling you something immediately.
他们没有立刻告诉你某件事。
It's you know, like when a person is trying to think, but you know, has a hard time and
就像，你知道，当一个人试图思考，但很难开口时。
they're really trying to explain something, but you know, it's just, well, you know what
他们真的在努力解释什么，但你知道，就是，嗯，你懂的。
I'm talking about.
我在说什么。
It's like that time with that thing where he did that.
就像那次他做那件事的时候那样。
Okay.
好吧。
This is really annoying.
这真的很烦人。
I know it's called beating around the bush because you just don't say what you're thinking.
我知道这叫拐弯抹角，因为你就是不直说你在想什么。
Right.
对。
Exactly.
没错。
So you don't say something directly.
所以你不直接说某事。
Now, our next phrase is to take into consideration.
现在，我们的下一个短语是“考虑到”。
Take something into consideration.
把某事考虑进去。
Well this is something that the young man brings up when he's asking for a raise.
嗯，这是那个年轻人在要求加薪时提到的。
He says, you should take into consideration all of these great things I do.
他说，你应该考虑到我做的所有这些好事。
This means when you make your decision, I want you to think about these things.
这意味着当你做决定时，我希望你考虑这些事情。
So consideration means you're thinking when you're trying to make a decision.
所以“考虑”意味着你在做决定时在思考。
To consider.
考虑。
All right.
好的。
So to take something into consideration or you can just say to consider.
所以“把某事考虑进去”或者你也可以直接说“考虑”。
So I'm interested in buying a new TV, but I have to take into consideration the fact
所以我想买一台新电视，但我必须考虑到
that I don't have a lot of money.
我没有很多钱这个事实。
That means I probably won't get a new TV.
这意味着我可能不会买新电视了。
I have to think about these things when I'm making my decision.
我在做决定时必须考虑这些事情。
Right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
非常好。
And our last phrase for today, towards the end, the boss was a little bit interested
今天我们最后一个短语，在对话结尾，老板有点
in knowing what happened or which companies were interested in him.
想知道发生了什么，或者哪些公司对他感兴趣。
So he said, just out of curiosity.
所以他说，“只是出于好奇”。
So this is something we say when we don't need to know something.
这是我们在不需要知道某事时说的话。
It means that we would like to know because we're curious, we're interested, but not because
意思是，我们想知道是因为我们好奇、感兴趣，而不是因为
I need to know right away what companies offer you jobs.
我需要马上知道哪些公司给你提供了工作。
So this is a polite way to ask why someone did something.
所以这是一种礼貌地问某人为什么做某事的方式。
So for example, so just out of curiosity, Marco, what kind of shampoo do you use?
比如，“只是出于好奇，Marco，你用哪种洗发水？”
That is very interesting knowledge that you want there.
你想知道的那个信息挺有意思的。
Well, obviously I don't need to know what kind of shampoo Marco uses, but I'm curious
嗯，显然我不需要知道Marco用什么洗发水，但我好奇
because maybe I'm going to buy a new kind of shampoo.
因为也许我要买一种新洗发水。
So you can start your sentence by using this phrase, just out of curiosity.
所以你可以用这个短语开始你的句子，“只是出于好奇”。
Just out of curiosity.
只是出于好奇。
It's a great one.
这是个很棒的短语。
Listen for that again as we listen to today's dialogue one more time, and we'll be back
当我们再听一遍今天的对话时，留意这个短语，我们稍后会回来
in a moment to talk about getting a raise.
讨论关于加薪的事。
Excuse me, sir.
打扰一下，先生。
May I talk to you?
我能和你谈谈吗？
Sure, come on in.
当然，进来吧。
What can I do for you?
有什么事吗？
Well, sir, as you know, I have been an employee of this prestigious firm for over 10 years.
嗯，先生，如您所知，我已经在这家知名公司工作了十多年。
Yes.
是的。
I won't beat around the bush, sir.
我就不拐弯抹角了，先生。
I would like a raise.
我想要加薪。
I currently have three companies after me, and so I decided to talk to you first.
目前有三家公司想挖我，所以我决定先和您谈谈。
A raise?
加薪？
Son, I would love to give you a raise, but this is just not the right time.
孩子，我很想给你加薪，但现在不是合适的时候。
I understand your position, and I know that the current economic downturn has had a negative
我理解您的处境，也知道当前经济低迷对销售产生了负面
impact on sales, but you must also take into consideration my hard work, proactiveness,
影响，但您也必须考虑到我十多年来的努力工作、积极主动
and loyalty to this company for over a decade.
和对公司的忠诚。
Taking into account these factors and considering I don't want to start a brain drain, I'm willing
考虑到这些因素，并且我不想引发人才流失，我愿意
to offer you a 10% raise and an extra five days of vacation time.
给你加薪10%，外加五天额外假期。
How does that sound?
你觉得怎么样？
Great.
太好了。
It's a deal.
成交。
Thank you, sir.
谢谢您，先生。
Before you go, just out of curiosity, what companies were after you?
在你走之前，只是出于好奇，哪些公司在挖你？
Oh, the electric company, the gas company, and the water company.
哦，电力公司、煤气公司和自来水公司。
All right.
好吧。
We're back.
我们回来了。
So interesting enough, he needed a raise not because three companies wanted to hire him,
有趣的是，他需要加薪不是因为三家公司想雇他，
but because he needed to pay his bills.
而是因为他需要付账单。
Well, this is funny because he's not talking about companies, that's right, who are offering
嗯，这很好笑，因为他说的不是提供工作机会的公司，
him jobs.
没错。
He's talking about the gas, the water, the electrical company.
他说的是煤气公司、自来水公司和电力公司。
It's a very funny dialogue, but I think asking for a raise is very hard to do because you
这是一个很有趣的对话，但我认为要求加薪很难做到，因为你
know that your boss is worried about money or it's a bad time to ask, but you want to
知道老板担心钱的问题，或者现在不是好时机，但你想
ask because it's important that you get the right compensation for your work.
提出来，因为得到与工作相称的报酬很重要。
And actually, it's important to have a clear objective when you want to ask for a raise.
实际上，当你想要加薪时，有一个明确的目标很重要。
So more or less what you want to earn, but plausible within the company.
所以大致是你想赚多少，但在公司内要合理。
So you're not going to ask for a 100% raise, right?
所以你不会要求加薪100%，对吧？
You can maybe aim for a 5 or 10% and most likely you'll get it if you negotiate properly.
你也许可以瞄准5%或10%，如果谈判得当，很可能得到。
That's right.
没错。
And sometimes a raise isn't just about money.
有时加薪不仅仅是钱的问题。
You can also, like he did, ask for some time off.
你也可以像他那样，要求一些休假时间。
So he gets some vacation days or perhaps some training or bonuses or a bonus.
所以他会有一些假期，或者也许是一些培训、奖金或一笔奖金。
So this all depends on the kind of negotiations that you make, but it's worth it to ask.
所以这完全取决于你谈判的方式，但问一问总是值得的。
So please let us know if you've ever had a good time or a bad time asking for a raise.
所以请告诉我们，你是否有过要求加薪的好经历或坏经历。
It can be a very nerve wracking experience.
这可能是一次非常紧张的经历。
I know personally I'm very uncomfortable with it, but we're excited to hear what you have
我个人知道，我对这件事非常不自在，但我们很期待听到你的
to say.
想法。
And if you have any questions or comments, leave them for us on our website, EnglishPod.com.
如果你有任何问题或评论，请在我们的网站 EnglishPod.com 上留言。
All right.
好了。
We'll see you guys there.
我们到时候见。
Bye everyone.
大家再见。
Goodbye!
再见！